Let's pray.
Well, good morning, everyone. How are we all doing?
Great.
Okay. A third of you are awake. How's everybody else doing?
All right. Okay, good. I was concerned for a moment. I was just telling Ryan, "You know you've been preaching at a church too much when they don't even give you intros anymore." You know what I mean?
He's like, "Nah, just get up there and just go." I was like, "Okay, cool." But I am getting spoiled with the intro music, although the last intro music was more epic, I felt.
This was a little more like your friendly neighborhood Sam, which is actually more appropriate, I guess.
Well, I'm glad to be here with you guys again, and sharing in part of this series on witness. And if you don't already know, I will plug this really quick.
As you're going through the series, and you're interested in it, and you're actually wondering, "Okay, what's a little more, maybe even some more practical conversations, and how can I team up with people to be expressing the gospel through my life and witnessing to others?"
I'm sure you guys have announced it for a few weeks now. We have a training coming up. It's a joint church training between my church and Canvas. It will be happening here.
I'll be mostly leading it, but Ryan will be jumping in along with my wife and helping to lead that. And it's going to be, you know, talking about, there it is, everyday mission.
I will say this to you now, just so that you know what you're getting into. Good news and bad news. Who wants the good news first?
Okay, who wants bad news first? Nope, it was a trick question. I'm giving you the good news first.
All right, so the good news, I asked, but I didn't care. It's like when I asked my kids a question, right? Like, where do you want to go for dinner?
And then they tell me, I'm like, we're not going there. Okay, so here's the good news. The good news is, this is not going to be a training where I give you another thing for your calendar,
or I give you, like, another deep book you've got to go into, or, like, a whole bunch of, like, things that are going to make you feel stressed
and overburdened with your daily life, okay? So that's the good news. It's not going to be any of that. Okay. You go, well, what could the bad news be?
The bad news is that this is also not a class where you are going to be comfortable. It's not a class where you're going to be able to
continue to think the way you've been thinking, or to even desire the things you've been desiring. Does it make sense?
So if you say, "Hey, I'm ready for, like, actual internal change in the way that I think, and the way that I desire, and the way that I'm thinking
about what my life is about," that is this. Because missional living is, like, 10% behavioral change, but, like, 90% thinking change.
You don't actually have to do a whole lot different. You are going to have to think radically differently about everything.
So there will be some role-playing. Who loves role-playing in classes? The answer is nobody. Nobody likes role-playing.
And every once in a while, there's, like, one or two people in the class that loves role-playing, and we know that person's the psycho.
The rest of us are normal. So you might go, "Okay, so then why is the role-playing?" Because it's one of those things that works.
I hate to say it, I was in sales for AT&T for, like, over a decade, and we would role-play sales conversations all the time.
And I'm like, "This is so dumb. Everyone hates role-playing." And it made me better at sales.
And so we're not selling anything, of course, but practicing. There will be some of that, so as a heads-up.
If you have a lot of social anxiety and that's a problem for you, get over it and come and, yeah, you're an adult now.
Mom and Dad aren't here anymore. For some of us, this guy's mom's still here, but it's not the same.
All right? But anyway, okay? So I encourage you for that. And there'll be food and hugs and encouragement,
and we're not going to be mean or anything, but we're going to get real. All right, so that does go into what we're talking about today.
So today, I'm going to be talking to you guys about witness, and specifically partnering with the Holy Spirit in our witness, which is, well, we're going to see today.
It's actually the most key part. Nothing else works if we're not doing this, and we'll understand why that is.
So I'm just going to give you the core concept for today's lesson, so you know where we're going, and then we're going to unpack it as we go. Sound good? Okay.
The core concept for today is that witness is not about bringing God to people, right?
Now, that hopefully will alleviate a little bit of a burden, because a lot of us will be like, "I don't know how to bring God to people."
And they're out there living their lives, and I'm like, "Here's some Jesus." And they're like, "I'm not sure if I want that, because He has rules."
And so we feel this pressure. It's on me to bring God to people, okay?
We think that because we don't...we're too much in our own heads and not enough in the Scripture.
This is not what the Scripture teaches at all, so that's the good news.
Witness is not about bringing God to people. Witness is actually about bringing yourself to God's work, which is already in process, okay?
So, God's already there. He doesn't need you to bring Him to anybody.
I don't know if you've noticed this, but God's, like, never really needed you for anything.
And He will continue to not need you for anything, okay? But He will invite you into what He's doing.
And if we can just understand that, then we can go, "Oh, wow, a lot of that front-loaded burden that's kind of discouraging me
and intimidating me just kind of comes off." Because it turns out I'm just...this is an analogy I use all the time.
How many of us have had small children at some point in our lives, in our home? Okay, great. Yes, God bless you.
Okay? How many of you have had your small children, like, under the age of four, help you with things around the house?
Okay? And you've invited them to help you, right? If you've done that, then you know that the small child makes every task harder
and longer and less efficient and worstly done. Okay? And so, the child is inviting in because of the desire for relationship
and training and development of the child, not because that child is actually helping at all, right?
It's like if you wanted to help, like one time I was changing my tire, and my son who was four was like,
"Let me help you, daddy." And I was like, "That's not what you're about to do." But sure. You know what I'm saying?
Because the tire weighs like five of you, and so you're not going to be very helpful at all.
Everything we ever do in ministry is the equivalent of the four-year-old helping dad change the tire.
You understand that? If God was just about efficiently getting the world saved,
he would tell you to go take a nap, and you would wake up, and it would all be done, okay?
So he has a different goal there, but all right. Okay, you know what? Sermon's over in five minutes.
That's it. That's pretty much it. Now what we're going to do is I'm going to use the Bible
to prove to you that I didn't just make all that up, all right? How's that? Is that good? Okay.
Brian said, "We need it to be shorter today, Sam." And I said, "Not because of me."
Well, you know, sometimes. We've got to be thoughtful of the kids.
There we go. Five minutes. Record time. Let's all go to Taco Bell. Anybody? Okay.
I don't know what he is. After I'm done preaching, I know it's not good for you,
but I want Taco Bell every time I'm done preaching. Is that just me?
Okay. Okay. We're just going right into confession. The sermon's over.
All right. So, witness is not bringing God to people. It is bringing yourself.
To God's work, which is already in progress in a person's life, okay?
So, as we've kind of alluded to already, witness is one of those things.
Sharing our faith. There's that scary word evangelism, right?
It is that thing, if I were to sit up here and tell you that you should do it, you already know, right?
We already know that we should be doing it. If we're being totally honest, we just don't want to.
Now, that might make you sound like a terrible person at face value, but we're going to unpack.
Let's really think about why don't we want to, right?
Because we all feel guilty for not doing it. Like, every time there's a sermon series, like, we're going to be talking,
I'm sure when Ryan was like, we're going to be doing a four-week series, four weeks, right?
Four-week series on witness, probably some part of your heart goes, "Great.
Now I'm going to be reminded of what a failure of a Christian I am, because I never do this.
I don't want to do it. I know I should, right?" So we feel guilty for not doing it, but we're also afraid to do it.
Raise your hand. It's a safe space, guys. No one's going to judge you.
How many of you would say, if you're being totally honest, you're partly or even mostly just afraid to do it?
Yeah. All right. Look at that. Look, support, right? We're all on the same team.
Okay, don't feel bad. You're afraid to do it. And so we feel stuck and discouraged, right?
Like one of those things I know I should do, but I'm scared to do it. I know how to do it.
Okay, so that's where we're at. Our reasons tend to boil down to a few common issues.
Either we don't know what to say, and we feel a pressure to say everything right.
I think that's a really common one. Like somebody's salvation and eternal life is on the line, and I don't know my Bible that well.
And, of course, we've ignored the fact that we at least know enough to believe it ourselves.
So we actually know a whole lot more than what we think we do, okay?
But we don't know what to say, and we feel like everything's riding on our word choice.
That's one of the reasons people are terrified of public speaking, right?
It's one of the reasons, because you feel this weight to the words you're about to say from the stage.
And so you're intimidated by that, because you feel like it's all riding on you to get everything right.
Afraid of rejection and humiliation, right?
Because what if I try it, and then I say something, and then I, like, veer off into heresy.
Like, I don't know, I was using colors and stuff. Like, I don't even know what I was talking about, right?
And so we're worried about being humiliating. You know, what if I give this person my best, and they're like, "I don't want it."
Or we carry the burden of the results, which is kind of what this all boils down to, right?
We carry the burden of the results, meaning we think that the success of our witness is up to us.
This is another point of encouragement I'll just say kind of quickly.
Don't you think it would be incredibly unloving of God to leave somebody else's life in your hands,
and depending on how well you phrase something? Like, if we really thought about it, for that to be true,
God would have to not care about people at all. I'm just gonna let it sink in, guys, because we all think it's true, though.
But if it were true, it would require God to not care about anybody. You know what I'm saying?
Like, I'm still figuring out how to not eat too many cookies, guys. And God's gonna leave it up to me whether somebody lives or dies, receives the gospel.
He knows who he's dealing with. You know what I mean? And so, but we do. We carry the burden of the results, but I think success is up to us.
And so in the meantime, people within arms reaching, I just want us to like emotionally grapple with the reality of these feelings.
In the meantime, people within arm's reach of us, where we work, where we live, where we play, where we hang out, are lost in suffering.
It's not theoretical. It's not academic. The people that you know and you see on a daily basis in the places where you live and work, they're lost in their suffering.
And somehow we convince ourselves, "Well, they don't really seem like they're lost in suffering."
It's like, "Oh, yeah, because, you know, one of the hallmarks of humanity is how honest we are about what's going on inside of us, right?"
No one in this room has ever been, like, doing terrible and then showed up with a smile on their face on Sunday morning, like, "We don't do that."
That's crazy talk. Yeah. So just because your coworkers and your neighbors seem fine, they're not.
Nobody apart from Christ is okay. Right? So while we're sitting here hemming and hawing, like, "I don't know if I can say the thing that I need to say,"
"at the right moment." The reality on the ground is people are within arm's reach, guys.
I'm not talking about people across the world. Those are the responsibility of the believers who live over there.
I'm talking about people within arm's reach of you. Yeah, you haven't been called to save the world.
You've not really been called to save anybody, but you have been called to witness to the people that God has put you next to, right?
These people are responsibilities. People are lost in suffering.
And so here we stand paralyzed in like our fear and insecurity like lifeguards watching people drown, right?
Like if you watched a lifeguard standing and watching somebody drown, you're like, "Why aren't you jumping in?"
They're like, "He looks heavy. I'm not sure if I can swim strong enough."
You'd just be like, "Well, do something," right? And that's us.
And so gradually we have learned to distract ourselves from the people who are dying around us.
Or to convince ourselves like it's somebody else's job, right?
"Hey, I know we're called to witness, but you know, that's not really my gift."
Anyone ever say that? Okay, you can raise your hand. It's still safe, okay?
It's not really my gift. You know, Ryan's called to that. You know, he's got a gift for that man.
I'm just gonna go make a potluck for us after we're dying, and that's my gift. I got to get to hospitality."
Those are all real, by the way. You know, people really do have gifts for those things.
Witness is not one of those things that you really get to a gift. It's a part of your identity.
That's something we'll be talking about the first week of training, right?
Witness flows out of your identity, not out of some gifting that you may or may not have.
And so we'll find all these excuses, but it's really flowing from the fact that we're afraid and we feel we're carrying a pressure and we believe we have a role that we don't have.
So my goal today is to help us kind of take that way off and realize, "Oh, I've been largely intimidated because I've misunderstood my role in the witness process."
And if we can understand our role, it is, I can tell you, tremendously less intimidating and a lot more hopeful.
So we do. We fundamentally misunderstand our role.
I'm going to summarize for you. You guys might know in the Gospel of John, chapter 4, a really famous story where Jesus is with the woman at the well.
You guys know the story? Okay. So I'm not going to read the whole chapter. I'm going to sum up. Can I sum up? Okay.
So, right, so Jesus is going, you know, they've been walking for a long time. He needs some water.
He stops at a well, middle of the day, by himself. Lady comes up, and he strikes up a conversation with her.
That's all he does. "Hey, I don't have any ability to get water from this well.
You have the rope in the bucket. Can I have some water?"
She's like, "Why are you asking me for water?" Opportunity. Jesus is like, "Great question.
Actually, you should be asking me for water." She's like, "What are you talking about?"
And he's like, "I have a water that will make you never thirsty again." She's like, "Okay." Right?
And he's like, "Go get your husband." And then she's like, "I don't have a husband." He's like, "Yeah, actually, that's true,
because you've had five, and the guy you're living with now isn't your husband."
So then she goes, "I perceive that you are like a prophet." Right? Because he knows these things.
And then she uses the fact that he's a prophet to leverage into a conversation
that she's obviously been struggling with, which is, "Hey, you Jews say that we have nowhere to worship
because there's only one place we can, and you won't let us go there."
So now this other, now two deep-seated bothering things in her life, right?
Her marital history and situation, and now the fact that not only am I going through all this mess in my life,
but I also feel like I don't even have a place to worship
because the one place I'm supposed to worship is the place you guys say I'm not allowed to go.
And you guys hear the opportunities in the conversation?
All stemming from, "I just started talking to you," right?
And then he's like, "I'm glad you brought that up, because actually, because I'm here,
that whole location thing doesn't matter anymore," right?
Because let me tell you about who God really is,
and if you understood who he really was,
you would realize that rule that Jews have doesn't even matter anymore.
Not with me, right?
And so she gets all excited, and she's like, "You know, that's some good prophecy.
You know, when the Messiah comes, he's gonna make everything make sense."
And Jesus is like, "I got good news for you. He's already here."
And she runs off into her town, and she tells everything she knows.
And then his disciples come, and they're like, "You need to eat."
And he's like, "No, I don't because my food," and this is, "I want us to internalize this for ourselves," right?
Jesus goes, "I don't need to eat anything, man.
My food is to do what the Father has sent me to do and to finish the work that he's doing," right?
And so this is the thing we see play out with Jesus and that woman.
What did he actually do in the story? Was it anything truly extraordinary?
I mean, besides the fact that he clearly had divine revelation about her life, right?
Which is available to all of us. I'll give you that in a moment.
Besides that, anything crazy? Any crazy miracles?
Comes walking across the lake to her, you know, floating down from heaven, you know, like an angel posse at his back.
Nothing nuts, guys. He's having a normal conversation with her, and he's letting the Spirit lead where that conversation goes.
Right? He was present. He was, okay. We all know what this is, right? Okay.
He was present. He was present. He's paying attention. Don't let me forget that. Okay. He was present.
Later my wife's going to be calling me. I'm very concerned. He was present. He was paying attention. He was tuned in to his father's work.
He asked questions. He asked questions. He listened. And he spoke the truth of God at the right moment.
Right? He didn't like roll up to the well and be like, "What's up? I'm the Messiah. Your life is changing."
There would have been no context for that. Right? So he's paying attention. He's pressing. He's listening. Right?
And he's speaking the truth of God at the right moment. Now, at this point, you might go, "Yeah, Sam. Sure. Yeah. Son of God.
Okay. High standard here. Sure. He was Jesus. Give me something more relatable." Right? Anyone, if you're feeling that in your body for a moment,
you're like, "I don't feel like it's a good example, Sam." You're basically telling me, "Be just like Jesus," saying, "I'm not doing so well at that." Okay.
Also, keep in mind that the work of Jesus throughout the Gospels is consistently, and there were so many Scripture references,
like I didn't even want to like list them all because there'd just be like two columns on the slide. Consistently,
the Gospel writers make it clear that even though He is God, every single thing that Jesus did, He did through the power of the Holy Spirit. Every single thing.
Before you see Him do crazy things, you'd be like, "And then Jesus went out, full of the Holy Spirit." Right? And then even Luke 4:18-19,
when you read the prophecy from Isaiah, what is the prophecy? "The Spirit of the Lord is on me to proclaim freedom and healing and deliverance." Right?
And so, if we want to look and go, "Sam, not a good example. That's the Son of God. That's not me. I'm still intimidated."
He did everything. He could have done it by His own power. There's a reason He's doing it this way.
Everything He did, He did by the power of the Holy Spirit. Right? Here's the reason. Let's look at John 16.
I'm sorry, this is later in the book. John 16:7-14. This is Jesus speaking.
He says, "But in fact, it is best for you that I go away, because if I don't, the advocate won't come."
That's the Holy Spirit. Anyone ever feel sometimes where it'd be like, "Wouldn't it be better if Jesus just, like, stayed and hung out with us?"
I feel like it'd be so much better. Not according to Him. He says to His disciples, "It's actually better for you if I go.
Because when I go, I'm going to go stand beside the throne. I'm going to sing the Holy Spirit to you." Right?
If I do go away, then I will send Him to you. Verse 8, "And when He comes, He," not you, "He will convict the world of its sin, and of God's righteousness, and of the coming judgment.
The world's sin is that it refuses to believe in Me. Righteousness is available because I go to the Father, and you will see Me no more.
Judgment will come because the ruler of this world has already been judged."
"There is so much more I want to tell you, but you can't bear it now. And when the Spirit of truth comes, He will guide you into all truth.
He will not speak on His own, but will tell you what He has heard. He will tell you about the future, and He will bring Me glory by telling you whatever He receives from Me."
Okay, so quick recap. Because again, remember the problem I'm telling you, the reason that we're intimidated by witness is because we misunderstand our role.
So, first we want to look at what is the Holy Spirit's role in disciple making. I'm going to use the term disciple making beyond just witness, because that's what we're actually trying to do, right?
I'm a disciple, you're a disciple, and our job is to make more, right? Just like I'm a human, you're a human, one of the jobs of humans is to make more humans and raise more humans, and it keeps going, right? Otherwise, there's no more people, right?
It's true about you physically, it's true about you spiritually, right? So, the Holy Spirit's job in disciple making is laid out right here. It's to draw attention to Jesus.
You guys notice that? Like, Holy Spirit, the Father, the Son, they're all one. And yet, Jesus is like, when he comes, this is what he's going to be doing, constantly drawing back.
He's not going to be giving you new stuff. It's just going to be pointing back to me, pointing back to me, pointing back to me, right?
So, his attention is, the Holy Spirit's role is to draw attention to Jesus, to convict and convince people of the truth.
This is another burden off of you, right? You know, I don't know if I can convince people. That's okay. It's not your job.
Your job is not to convict or convince anybody. He says the Holy Spirit's going to do that. And you, I don't know what to say.
Jesus answers that too. He's going to tell you what to say, right?
Guys, can I just say, it's almost like, I'm just going to say, it's almost like if we, like, slow down and read the Bible, like a lot of these questions would be answered.
So, if you're sitting there being like, "Wow, Sam has so much knowledge and experience." No, I just, I've read the book, okay?
Don't be impressed by me, okay? These are the words of the Lord. He has spelled it out so clearly for us, okay?
So, the Holy Spirit's role is to draw attention to Jesus, to convict and convince people of the truth, and to educate us on what to say.
Now, we've already read this next passage. I'm going to go to it again. 1 Corinthians 2:1-5.
Now, we're going to see Paul talking about, like, how he played that out in his life, right?
And we could read Paul's letters and be like, "Man, Paul was like a powerhouse, dude.
Like, put that guy on a stage, and he's probably just blowing people away."
And, like, Paul probably just, like, struggled around with, like, mad confidence and, like, always knew what to say in every city he went to go.
And, like, I bet Paul never struggled at all. Yeah, okay. That's not what Paul said.
1 Corinthians 2:1, Paul said, "When I first came to you, dear brothers and sisters,
I did not use lofty words or impressive wisdom to tell you God's secret plan."
This is very culturally relevant to them. It's also very culturally relevant to us.
You guys know how, like, enamored and in love we are with speaking, right?
If I had a dollar every time somebody sent me some video or some sermon or some TED Talk where they're like,
"You've got to listen to this guy." It's such an incredible message. And I listen to her and I go,
his or her skill in public speaking, yes, phenomenal. Content, it was a giant marshmallow.
There's nothing on the inside. No content. If you go to YouTube, there's this one really clever thing where this guy gives a TED Talk
on how to make people think that you're saying something of substance in a TED Talk.
It's genius. He illustrates his point so well.
We're so enamored with how well someone presents, and how persuasive their language is, and their stage presence,
whatever it is, that we don't stop to realize, like, are they actually saying anything? Right?
This is our culture, so we can definitely relate. This was also the culture that Paul was dealing with, right?
Like, the ancient Greeks, like, they loved the stage presentation and speaking. It was a big part of their culture.
And so that's why Paul was like, "I actually decided on purpose to not overthink what I was going to say,
to not plan exactly the right, perfect way of phrasing it." He goes, "For I decided that while I was with you,
I would forgive everything except Jesus Christ, the one who was crucified.
I came to you in weakness, timid and trembling, and my message and my preaching were very plain."
You might go, "I can't go and share, Sam. I'm going to be all, like, shaky and nervous." Cool.
The person will probably think that you have something really important to say to them
because of your strong emotional reaction. By the way, that's actually, like, psychologically true, right?
So Paul's like, "I did it too. Like, I was doing this."
My message and my preaching were very plain. Rather than using clever and persuasive speeches,
I relied only on the power of the Holy Spirit. I dig this. This is so important.
You might go, "Why does God work this way? Here's why He works this way."
I dig this so that you would trust not in human wisdom, but in the power of God, right?
Not just like the persuasive academic arguments for theology and faith.
Here's I don't even want you convinced of that. Guys, demons are convinced of those arguments.
You understand that? Who cares about knowing God the way that a demon knows God?
Right? He said, "I want you to have confidence in the power of God."
In other words, you've experienced what's actually being proclaimed.
You haven't just heard about it or intellectually agreed with it, right?
So what is our role in disciple making? Rely on the Holy Spirit.
And I'm going to unpack this as we close. How do I actually do this, okay?
Rely on the Holy Spirit. Attuned, you can think of it that way, to Him and empowered by Him.
That's your first role. Rely on the Holy Spirit. You're attuned to Him.
And you're empowered by Him. Embrace simplicity. Not complicated, right?
When that Samaritan woman went back to her village, how much did she have to say?
How much of the gospel did she know? How much Scripture could she quote?
She went back and she goes, "You have got to come meet this guy who just told me everything I ever did."
That's what she had. Embrace simplicity. Join with the Spirit and pointing people to Christ, right?
Well, what about this? What about that? I don't know. I don't know, man.
I would like to talk to you about Jesus, you know? And then finally, yeah, be courageous.
Okay? Paul spoke while timid and trembling. That's courage. Right? Okay. You're going to have to be courageous.
Push through timidity and insecurity. Remember, we are not called to intellectually persuade people.
Guys, we would have so many more genuine disciples of Christ if intellectual persuasion was effective in the kingdom of God.
Okay? As we sit right here, hundreds of thousands, millions of Americans are sitting and listening to sermons.
And most of them are probably pretty good and biblically sound. What percentage of that pie are genuine disciples of Christ?
I don't know. I know it's not all of them. Right? So, you're not called to just intellectually persuade people. We are called to partner with the Holy Spirit
and proclaiming, and, this is a whole other sermon. So, I don't know. We'll talk about this later.
And demonstrating. You're called to proclaim and to demonstrate the transformational power of God.
All right. So, I'm going to, in the last few minutes, I'm going to try and quickly work through this.
Is everybody ready to drink from a fire hose? Everybody? Okay? Because this could be a whole series,
and I'm just going to give you the cliff notes, and we can talk more later. Come to the training. Okay? Okay.
It's not, the sermon's not a tease. I don't mean it as a tease to, like, get you into the training. Okay?
How do we partner with the Holy Spirit? Working with the Holy Spirit. Here's what I want you to understand.
Again, it's simple. It's not very complicated. Working with the Holy Spirit flows from living in the Spirit. Okay?
The word I used earlier was to attune. Right? One of my old pastor friends, he said it this way. He goes,
you can almost kind of think of it like the Holy Spirit is a radio broadcast. It's always broadcasting.
The question is, have I grabbed my dial and tuned in? Because a lot of times we're like, Holy Spirit's not speaking.
He didn't tell me anything. Probably not the case. It doesn't take days off. He's not napping. Right?
He's always at work in the lives of the people around you. It's really just me. It's like, I don't know how to tune in. Right?
So that's living in the Spirit. I'm just going to throw some Scriptures at you. Okay? And if you take notes, jot these down.
First, we have to continually stir up what the Holy Spirit has placed in us. This is what Paul wrote to Timothy.
You know, Timothy's a young pastor. He's a direct mentee of Paul, right? Paul's writing to him.
And he says, "Timothy, listen, when I prayed and laid my hands on you, the Holy Spirit put gifts into you.
Now what you have to do is stir those up." Because let me tell you what God hasn't given you when I laid my hands on you.
He didn't give you a spirit of fear. He gave you a spirit of power and love and self-control or self-discipline.
Right? This is so wonderful. The Holy Spirit's actually going to empower me to manage myself.
Which is something that has been very hard on my own, right?
So we have to stir up what the Holy Spirit's placed inside of us, and we have to keep in step with him by pursuing holiness.
And what I mean by that is, you know, as I'm thinking about the things in my life, I'm pursuing that.
And I'm just going, you know, the more and more that I do my own internal work to get these besetting things,
and these unnecessary weights off of me, the more that I'm able to keep pace with the Spirit, right?
If you follow that metaphor. And so Galatians 5 talks about that.
By the way, when you read Galatians 5, the gifts of the Spirit, you know, love, joy, peace, patience, okay?
Self-control, it's in there again, right?
Don't read that as a list of, like, to-dos that you've got to go work on.
And I would argue, don't even read it as a list of, like, nine different fruits.
It's better to understand it this way.
It is one fruit, and Paul is turning around trying to describe what it looks like.
Does it make sense? Okay.
And that is a fruit that grows naturally from the plant.
So he's like, here's how you know. If you're like, how do I know I'm except with the Spirit?
Take a quick inventory. Am I loving? Am I patient? Am I kind? Am I self-controlled?
No, I'm not any of those things. Oh, okay, red flag. I'm probably not except with the Holy Spirit.
Let me go get back in return with Him and get in step with Him.
How do we do that? Great question. I'm glad you asked.
We do this by staying in a rhythm of prayer, okay?
You know, we always talk about like, "Pray and read your Bible."
And everyone's like, "Oh, why am I supposed to do that? It feels like a chore."
There's a practical reason to pray and read your Bible.
It is how you tune into the Holy Spirit, okay?
As you begin to practice in prayer, and prayer becomes a regular, not occasional, and not an emergency aspect of your life.
You know, praying when everything is great. Praying when you're not stressed.
Praying is a rhythm of your life, coupled with regular attention to Scripture, right?
We see it right there. Pray in the Spirit at all times and on every occasion, right? Being alert, right?
So it's a constant rhythm of prayer in my life. And then also through Scripture study, like 2 Timothy 3:16, right?
If you go, "Well, I don't know what the Holy Spirit sounds like. I have great news for you."
He has written about 1,500 pages of text. It's been available to us for 2,000 years.
And you can even get it for free on your phone right now, okay?
So, the more that you absorb Scripture into your life, you are teaching yourself,
"How does God sound when He talks?" Because at any given time, I have like three voices in my head.
I have mine, which is usually pretty dumb. I have God, which is always great. And I have the enemy.
And part of my job is to learn how I do it. I'm turning the radio station.
How do I know which one I'm tuned into right now? As I'm studying the Scripture, I'm learning that bandwidth.
Does that make sense? I'm learning that frequency, okay? So, that's the practical thing to it, okay?
Remember, so, working with the Spirit flows from living in the Spirit, okay?
We also must learn to slow down, not rushing past people, not always focused on our agenda, and not always on to the next thing.
Okay? The work of God and the work of witness is slow. And we're Americans, and we're in everything fast, and we want to scale production, and we want to get like, "I got 10 people saved this week, next week we got 100 people saved." Stop it!
The Bible isn't American. The Bible is not consumeristic. The Bible is not capitalist. None of those are necessarily bad things.
They're just not the Bible. Okay? The work of the kingdom is slow work. The way more people get saved is that more people are doing slow work. Does that make sense?
The work that you're doing in the lives of other people is never going to speed up. It's never going to become exponential. This takes time.
And so you have to commit to the long haul and go, "The Lord has given me a slow work in people's lives." I might be friends with this person for two years before they are even interested in talking to me about God.
But I'm going to be faithful. I'm going to be attuned to the Holy Spirit. I'm looking for the opportunity, right? And the whole time I'm intentional, right?
They think we're just hanging out, and we are just hanging out, but also I'm like listening to the Lord. You got something for me here? Make sense? Okay, so it's a slow work.
As we live in the Spirit, we will become attuned to His voice and promptings, right? He is at work. And this is something we have to choose to believe. He is at work in the lives of the people around us.
And you might go, "I don't see it, Sam. I don't see Him at work." I know. Back to attunement, right?
We have got to start with the belief that He is at work, right? In the lives of the people we encounter, and He's actually positioning us for key moments, right?
So He's at work in their hearts already. He's also at work in me, just kind of orchestrating where I happen to find myself sometimes on a morning, right?
We believe this because this work is often invisible to us until we get in step with Him. The Spirit will draw out your attention.
If you begin to tune in, and you begin to actually slow down, put your phone away, stop thinking about what needs to happen next.
By the way, can we just be totally honest? Like 95% of the things on your agenda that are stressing you out, and are varying degrees of importance, sure.
If 95% of those things don't happen, is anybody dying? Are you going to be sleeping in a cardboard box tomorrow?
Are your children going to drive off the deep end? No. Yet we give them attention as if that is true, right?
So, slow down. Some things won't get done. It's okay. We got to make space for other things to be done. Make sense?
Because if we slow down and we start to look at the people around us, it will surprise you. I promise you this week, it will surprise you.
Be like, "Wow." It's kind of like when you buy a new car, and you think nobody else has that car, and then you start driving around.
We bought a white Honda Odyssey 2019, and my wife was like, "I'm so mad it's white." And I'm like, "Why?" She's like, "Because everyone in town has a white Honda Odyssey."
I'm like, "No, they don't. I've seen one of them." And she goes, "Trust me. We bought one, and I can't find my van in the parking lot."
Right? It's kind of like that. When you start to tune in the Holy Spirit, you're like, "Oh my gosh, he's talking all the time."
Okay? So it's just a matter of tuning in. He's going to draw your attention to people's conversations.
I don't like to eavesdrop, but there's times at Panera where I've been sitting there,
and I hear something going down over here. They're walking through something in their life. Right?
I'm like, usually I pray, because I'm not trying to be that guy. I have said things a couple times.
A couple times. But I also pray about that. I'm like, "Should I say anything, Lord?"
And he's like, "Just pray." I'm like, "Okay." I'll let that answer. That's what I'm going to do.
I'm going to just do that. I can't tell how much terrible life advice is given amongst friends at Panera.
Oh my gosh. I just want to be like everyone's dad. I'm sitting in there, I'm listening to these college kids talk,
and I'm like, "Don't do any of what your friend just said. It's going to go so badly."
Like, "Just do what's good for you." I'm like, "Don't do what's good for you. It's only good for the next three weeks,
and then you're going to hate everything." All right. Sorry.
So we're going to be doing the Holy Spirit. He's going to talk to us. We must be ready to do,
and I will say this to you, and again, this is where we can veer off and go a whole other conversation.
So, I mean, more later, okay? We must be ready to do whatever He says. You do have to determine that.
If you go out in public and you go, "Holy Spirit, I'm listening. Dial me in."
The likelihood that He's going to tell you things that you do not want to act on is incredibly high.
So you've got to make up your mind right away. I'm going to listen and obey. Right?
Can I tell you a super crazy thing that we're going to get to the end, and then we're stopping. Marissa's going to come up.
"Cool!" I told her that was going to be my signal for her coming to the piano.
And she was like, "I'm not actually going to do it." And I said, "No, let's do it. Let's do it." Okay?
Look over here. I'm going to tell you a crazy story. Okay.
It's not always going to be this crazy, guys. It's not always going to be this crazy. Okay?
But sometimes it's going to be crazy, and I want to prepare you for the crazy, right?
The good news is 90% of the time it's going to be kind of normal.
He might just say, "Go talk to that person. Ask them how they're doing."
I used to direct a youth camp. I've been a youth pastor for, like, 13 years.
And there was this girl. I don't know if I told a story out loud. I hope she's fine with it.
There was this girl who I knew had been cutting herself
because she'd been wearing long sleeves the whole couple of months.
And, you know, we're having, like, ministry time, and people are praying. And I heard the Lord say,
"Hey, I want you to go over to her and pull up her sleeve,
and I want you to rub your tears on the scars."
No, no.
That's weird. Borderline creepy.
Also, I don't know if you're noticing this, Lord, but I'm not crying.
And that went on for several minutes, and usually when I'm not obeying it,
my chest begins to feel like it's like an advice, right? That's the sensation.
That's like the signal God gave me for like you being disobedient.
If we're just gonna put the ribcage, we're gonna squeeze, right?
And so finally I go, okay, but I still, like I start walking towards her, and I'm still like,
but I don't have tears, so I don't know what's gonna happen there.
And the moment I took one step, I started crying like crazy.
And I just, I'd known this girl by the way since she was like nine. She was now like 15, so it wasn't like a total stranger.
But the moment I walked over there, I started doing it, and that's what I did, right?
And Lord did something to her that night.
I didn't even actually do anything. I then, 'cause you know, I like to pastor and preach and teach and like advise and, you know, give counsel.
I then was sitting there like, "Okay, Lord, now you're gonna give me like incredibly powerful things to say to her."
And he was like, "No, I'm not."
Nope.
And I was kind of frustrated in the moment for a moment, right?
'Cause I'm like, why wouldn't you also, like, should I explain this?
This is weird, right? Should I explain it?
And he was like, "No, because again, what did Paul say?
I came to you not with persuasive words,
'cause I didn't want you to have confidence in my wisdom or any human wisdom,
but instead that you would have confidence in the power of God, right?
I've not seen this girl for several years.
I honestly don't know how she's doing, right?
I hope well.
But you also understand that's the work of the Lord, not the work of Sam, right?
He didn't say, "And now, mentor her for the next 15 years until she has children around.
She's a fully formed, healthy adult."
I believe that's God's goal for her.
And I also believe that he has moved other people, right?
So this is the last thing I want to say.
Remember, as you're thinking through this, it's not on you to go the whole mile, right?
It's not on you to go the whole journey.
It's on you to go as a part of my identity of somebody, you know, one who is in Christ, right?
Filled with the Spirit.
The Holy Spirit is at work in this person's life.
And at various times and in various ways, he's going to say, "Hey, hey,
you, go do this."
Okay, good.
And he's doing the work, right?
So as we think about that, we just want to dial that in.
God is going to use you to proclaim the gospel and demonstrate the gospel.
This means more than just your lifestyle.
It means people actually experience the healing and the deliverings that the gospel promises.
That's what he wants you to do, right?
Holy Spirit's doing all the work, and he's going to bring you in for a piece of it.
So as we think about our witness, that's what we're doing.
All right, so I'm going to give us an exercise.
As I'm saying this next part, I want everyone to get something out that you can use to write down, okay?
Whether it's your phone, like a little note app in your phone, if you're a pen and paper person, okay?
You're only going to write one word, so you don't even need a lot of space, okay?
So, but everyone do that, because I want us to imagine the kingdom of God being both heard and experienced.
Isn't that so much more compelling to your heart than just like I'm going to convey knowledge of God to people?
Isn't it so much more compelling to go, I can see those faces, and I can imagine what it would be like if they didn't only come to know about God, but they actually came to experience Him.
They didn't just hear that they can be healed, but they actually get healed, right?
They don't just hear that hope is possible, but they actually experience the hope and the transformation of their life.
Remember, right? Remember that. Imagine people coming to know the love and power of Christ, and actually experiencing it.
Like broken hearts healed, broken bodies healed. Broken relationships reconciled beyond what we thought was possible. These are the kinds of things we've been having.
You've got that, you've got that thing out in your hands. You're gonna write down something. Here's what you're gonna have us do.
And this is, this is gonna prove it, guys. This is gonna prove that I haven't just been spending the last 45 minutes making things up.
We're gonna slow down. We're gonna tune in. Okay?
The Holy Spirit is at work as we speak in the lives of people around you, people you work with, people you know.
What we're gonna do is we're gonna pause, and we're gonna ask Him to give us one name this week. One.
One name, one person in our lives where He is at work and inviting us to join Him in that work.
I want you to close your eyes. I want you to, as you're just, just imagine yourself just dialing into the radio station for a moment.
Lord, you're at work in the life of a person that I know.
No. Well, many people, this week, maybe it's today, show me the person's name and face where you're pointing me to them.
Pause on their face. Think about them. Write their name down.
Who is the person the Holy Spirit's cluing you into right now, where He's saying, "I'm already at work in their hearts.
I've already been speaking into their minds. They're prepped for you. They're prepped for a conversation."
I want you to go with them this week. I want you to say this, one thing, or do this.
You know what I'm saying? I don't even say anything.
We're going to pause on that, and I want you to write down their name, and then I'm going to pray for us.
So I'm going to give you guys a moment to do that.
Let's pray.
O Lord, may your spirit first pour your love and peace into our own hearts,
and give us courage this week, Lord, to allow the love and the peace and the healing power that you've poured
into us be poured out from us into the lives of this person that we've named. Pray for courage and for boldness,
Lord, and also that by your Spirit, you would instruct us and alleviate from us any burdens or expectations
that we're placing on this that are not from you. Help us to discern the difference between our voice
and your voice, to embrace the simplicity and the straightforwardness of the things you're going to guide
and directing us this week, and to trust you with the results. Lord God, if a person is saved and healed
and transformed, it is only by your Spirit, it is only by your power that that miracle can happen.
And so, Lord, we thank you for the privilege and the opportunity to see you at work in somebody else
and to partner in some small way with you in that. I thank you for these things, Lord.
I thank you for every person in this room, because you have called us and redeemed us to be a people who belong to you
and who are fit and ready for good works in our community. So I thank you for these things, Lord God.
I thank you for every person here. I pray that you would bless them and encourage them and lead them this week in your name. Amen.
All right.
Go to church, please.
Right on.